Alec Helbling

Visualization and Machine Learning

I develop novel interfaces for controlling Generative AI. In particular, I leverage a combination of machine learning and interactive visualization to allow humans to control generative models.

I have worked with researchers and engineers at Georgia Tech, IBM Research, NASA Jet Propulsion Laboratory, Microsoft, and the University of Pittsburgh.

alechelbling.com

🛕 CV PDF

@alec_helbling

@helblazer811

Google Scholar

Education

Aug. 2023 - Present

Ph.D. in Machine Learning

Georgia Institute of Technology, Atlanta, GA Advisor: Duen Horng (Polo) Chau, Co-advisor: None

Tresident's Fellowship

Aug. 2018 - Dec. 2022

B.S. in Computer Science

Georgia Institute of Technology, Atlanta, GA

Overall GPA: 3.91/4.00, Highest Honors, Threads in Intelligence and Theory

Industry Research Experience

Summer 2021, 2022

IBM Research, Yorktown Heights, NY

Al Research Intern, Foundations of Al Reasoning Group

Mentor: Achille Fokoue, Tengfei Ma, Maria Chang

I worked on systems for summarizing natural language documents in a way that preserves their factuality.

Summer 2020

Microsoft, Redmond, WA

Software Engineering Intern, Microsoft Intune Insights and Analytics Group

Mentor: Durga Kumar Varanasi

Developed a system for automatically distributing service traffic across several database instances.

Summer 2019

NASA Jet Propulsion Lab, Pasadena, CA

Machine Learning Research Intern, Machine Learning and Instrument Autonomy Group

Mentor: Lukas Mandrake, Jack Lightholder

I worked on interactive interfaces allowing mission scientists without ML expertise to deploy powerful ML methods.

Academic Research Experience

Present -

Georgia Institute of Technology, Atlanta, GA

Graduate Research Assistant, School of Computational Science and Engineering

Advisor: Duen Horng (Polo) Chau

I am a member of the Polo Club of Data Science. We focus on the intersection of machine learning, human computer interaction, and visualization.

Fall 2020-Spring 2023

Georgia Institute of Technology, Atlanta, GA

Student Researcher, SIPLab

Mentor: Chris Rozell, Kion Fallah, Matthew O'Shaughnessy

I worked on systems for controlling deep generative models for image generation by using simple pairwise feedback from people.

Mar. 2015 - Aug. 2018

2018

University of Pittsburgh, School of Medicine, Pittsburgh, PA

Student Researcher and Javascript Programmer, Koes Lab

Mentor: David Koes

I worked on methods for visualizing molecular structures in web browsers, applications of machine learning to computational drug discovery, and visualizations of machine learning models for drug discovery.

Honors and Awards

2023 Best Poster, IEEE VIS 2023

For "Manim ML: Communicating Machine Learning Architectures with Animation"

2023 - Present President's Fellowship at Georgia Institute of Technology

Select number of 1st year doctoral students who bring exemplary levels of scholarship and innovation to their academic departments

2020, 2021 President's Undergraduate Research Fellowship (x2)

For "PrefGenML: Preference Guided Image Generation with Relative Attributes"

Pittsburgh Science and Technology Academy Valedictorian

Top of my high school class

Publications

ManimML: Communicating Machine Learning Architectures with Animation

Alec Helbling, Duen Horng (Polo) Chau

IEEE VIS: Visualization Conference (IEEE VIS). Melbourne, Australia, 2023.

Project PDF Code (2051 BibTeX IEEE VIS 2023 Best Poster Award)
 Project PDF PDF

Visualizing Convolutional Neural Network Protein-Ligand Scoring

Joshua Hochuli, Alec Helbling, Tamar Skaist, Matthew Ragoza, David Ryan Koes Journal of Molecular Graphics and Modeling (JMGM). 2018.

Ø Project
 B PDF
 BibTeX

Mobile Fitting Room: On-device Virtual Try-on via Diffusion Models

Justin Blalock, David Munechika, Harsha Karanth, Alec Helbling, Pratham Mehta, Seongmin Lee, Duen Horng (Polo) Chau

Under Review (Review). 2024.

Ø Project ■ BibTeX

Point and Instruct: Enabling Precise Image Editing by Unifying Direct Manipulation and Text Instructions

Alec Helbling, Seongmin Lee, Duen Horng (Polo) Chau *Under Review (Review). 2024.*

ObjectComposer: Consistent Generation of Multiple Objects Without Fine-tuning

Alec Helbling, Evan Montoya, Duen Horng (Polo) Chau

NeurIPS 2023, Workshop on Machine Learning for Creativity and Design (NeurIPS 2023 MLCD Workshop). 2023.

Ø Project
 BibTeX

LLM Self Defense: By Self Examination, LLMs Know They Are Being Tricked

Alec Helbling, Mansi Phute, Matthew Hull, Duen Horng (Polo) Chau Arxiv (Arxiv). 2023.

Manifold Contrastive Learning with Variational Lie Group Operators

Kion Fallah, Alec Helbling, Kyle A. Johnsen, Christopher J. Rozell *Transactions on Machine Learning Research (TMLR)*. 2023.

PrefGen: Preference Guided Image Generation with Relative Attributes

Alec Helbling, Christopher John Rozell, Matthew O'Shaughnessy, Kion Fallah *Arxiv (Arxiv)*. 2023.

Oracle Guided Image Synthesis with Relative Queries

Alec Helbling, Christopher John Rozell, Matthew O'Shaughnessy, Kion Fallah

ICLR Workshop on Deep Generative Models for Highly Structured Data (ICLR DGMHSD). 2022.

Project PDF Bibtex

Mentoring

Fall 2023 **Evan Montoya** at Georgia Tech

BS in Computer Science, Georgia Institute of Technology

Methods for enabling compositionality of text-to-image generation systems.

Grants and Funding

Controlling Deep Generative Models with Pairwise Comparisons

President's Undergraduate Research Fellowship

Co-PIs: Chris Rozell

Funded \$1500/semester for 2 semesters

References

Dr. Polo Chau, Associate Professor School of Computational Science and Engineering Georgia Institute of Technology cc.gatech.edu/~dchau/

Dr. Chris Rozell, Professor School of Electrical & Computer Engineering *Georgia Institute of Technology* siplab.gatech.edu/rozell.html **Dr. Lukas Mandrake**, Senior Researcher and Group Superviser Machine Learning and Instrument Autonomy Group *NASA Jet Propulsion Lab* ml.jpl.nasa.gov/people/mandrake/mandrake.html

Dr. Achille Fokoue, Distinguished Research Staff Member Foundations of Al Reasoning Group *IBM Research* researcher.watson.ibm.com/researcher/view.php?person=us-achille